Sam Smith Collection
Yale Center for British Art, Rare Books and Manuscripts
- Paper Model Sets, Series IV
  - The Ship of Matrimony, 1973; Smith, Sam, 1908-; Crafts Advisory Committee; 1 perforated sheet; 23 x 31 cm. (Box 1, Folder 24)
    The sheet depicts a miniature boat, a man, and a woman. "The ship of matrimony is a do-it-yourself vessel created specially for the Crafts Advisory Committee." Includes instructions.
    Cut-out craft; Models (representations); Paper toys
  - Pleasure Boats of England, 1974; Smith, Sam, 1908-; Design Council; 1 pamphlet (4 perforated sheets, folded cover); 21 x 30 cm. Signed in black ink on reverse, "For Frances with Love Sam Nov 1975" (Box 1, Folder 25)
    "Designed specially for home Paper Boat Builders, Sam Smith genuine England 1974 ... All the parts you need to build four trim little craft: The Houseboat, Sea Trips, Idle Hearts and the Old Gaffer ... It will help if you have a knife for scoring along the lines and opening out the slots before assembly, a drop or two of glue to put on the tabs for a stronger job, and a pair of tweezers to hold the smaller parts if your fingers are all thumbs. Bon Voyage!"
    Paper toys; Cut-out craft; Models (representations); Begaye, Mary Frances
  - Fair Fun for All, 1976; Smith, Sam, 1908-; Crafts Advisory Committee; 4 sheets (3 perforated); 21 x 30 cm. (Box 1, Folder 26)
    "Fair Fun for All, Sam Smith's simple press-out paper steam roundabout and sideshow attractions, all the parts you need to build the Waterloo Gallopers, the Bearded Lady show, Annie Oakley's shooting range, Gipsy Mona's caravan and the candy floss stall." Includes one sheet of instructions. The remaining sheets are perforated and contain the parts for building.
    Models (representations); Cut-out craft; Paper toys
  - Article from the Observer: "Sam's circus", 1977 November 13; The Observer, London; 1 leaf; 21 x 12 cm. (Box 1, Folder 27)
    Magazine clipping. Includes an image of Smith in his workshop and an image of his boat wood carvings and an assembled set of Fair Fun for All.
    Magazines (periodicals); Clippings; Smith, Sam, 1908-; Crafts Advisory Committee
- Carved and Painted Wood Sculpture, Series V
  - Shirley, ca. 1965; Smith, Sam, 1908-; 1 wood-carved sculpture, 1 stand; 11 x 20 cm. on stand Hand painted wood-carved sculpture (with string), of a boat with three men and a fish. The name Shirley is painted on the bow. Sits on unpainted stand. (Box 2)
    Blue and black painted boat named Shirley holds three men, attached to a string is their catch, a fish with painted red lips. This is one example of Smith's pre-occupation with the sea and his love for hand-made toys.
    Carvings (visual works); Primitivism (artistic concept); woodcarving; Boats; Toys (recreational artifacts)
  - Zebra, ca. 1975; Smith, Sam, 1908-; 1 woodcarving, 1 stand; 18 x 26 cm. Hand painted wood-carved sculpture (with string), of a boat with two primitive figures and a fish. The name Zebra is painted on the bow. Sits on unpainted stand. (Box 2)
    Black, brown, white and red painted boat named Zebra holds two bobble-head primitive figures, attached to a string is their catch, a brown and blue painted fish. This is one example of Smith's pre-occupation with the sea and his love for hand-made toys.
    Primitivism (artistic concept); Boats; woodcarving; Carvings (visual works); Toys (recreational artifacts)
  - No Fly Posters/No Bill Stickers, 1961; Smith, Sam, 1908-; 1 assemblage; 49 x 14 cm. Hand manipulative assemblage made of painted wood, fabric, string, sequins, nails, and pins. (Box 3)
    This multi-media assemblage is designed to be viewed on either of two sides depending on how it is being held. One side depicts a dark haired, blue eyed, female head wearing fake pearls and holding a sign stating, "No Bill Stickers". When turned around, the opposite side depicts the head of a dark haired, red eyed, moustached man holding a sign stating, "No Fly Posters". During this time period, Sam Smith created similar objects which he called mood-indicators. These objects were two-sided, wooden, peg-style heads, meant to be turned one way or the other to show either a happy or unhappy face.
    woodcarving; Assemblages (sculpture); Carvings (visual works); Primitivism (artistic concept)
- Exhibition Material, Series VI
  - Sam Smith exhibition catalog, 1972; City Art Gallery, Bristol; brochure (24 pages); 21 x 21 cm. Perforated cover designed to be removed and used to assemble a face mask. 2 copies. (Box 1, Folder 28)
    Exhibition catalog for Sam Smith, published independently by the City Art Gallery, Bristol. Introduction written by Arnold Wilson, Director of City Art Gallery, Bristol at the time of publication. Biographical forward written by Sam Smith, followed by images of some of his works and a list of objects from the exhibition. Presented by the Arkwright Arts Trust and financed by the London Borough of Camden. The exhibition venues and dates are as follows: City Art Gallery, Bristol, 4th May - 27th May 1972; Beaford Arts Centre, Devon, 5th June - 30th June; Camden Arts Centre, London, 12th July - 16th August.
    Brochures; Exhibition catalogs; Smith, Sam, 1908-; City Art Gallery, Bristol
  - Sam Smith exhibition catalog, 1980; Ernest Benn Ltd; Arts Council of Great Britain; booklet; 20 x 18 cm. (Box 1, Folder 29)
    "Published by Ernest Benn Limited in cooperation with the Arts Council of Great Britain on the occasion of an exhibition at the Serpentine Gallery, London 5 December 1980 to February 1981"--title page. Catalog accompanied by a typescript note, "sent at the request of Mr. Eric Lister" on Serpentine Gallery/Arts Council of Great Britain stationary.
    Exhibition catalogs; Brochures; Lister, Eric; Smith, Sam, 1908-; Serpentine Gallery
  - "Relics of Lost Gaiety" from The Daily Telegraph Magazine, 1972 July 28; Daily Telegraph (London); 3 leaves (6 pages); 31 x 25 cm. (Box 1, Folder 30)
    "Relics of Lost Gaiety" features Sam Smith and his wood carvings. Article advertises that, "Well over 100 of Sam Smith's objects are on display at the Camden Arts Center in London until August 16." Clipping is missing the continuation on page 28.
    Clippings; Camden Arts Centre; Smith, Sam, 1908-
  - The Daily Telegraph Magazine, 1972 July 28; Daily Telegraph (London); 1 volume; 31 x 25 cm. (Box 1, Folder 31)
    Magazine is marked in ink; "see p. 22" The Sam Smith article, "Relics of Lost Gaiety" are on pages 22-25, continued on 28. Article features Sam Smith and his wood carvings and advertises that, "Well over 100 of Sam Smith's objects are on display at the Camden Arts Center in London until August 16."
    Magazines (periodicals); Camden Arts Centre; Smith, Sam, 1908-
- Correspondence, Series VII
  - Letter to Eric Lister, 1972 July 7; Smith, Sam, 1908-; 1 leaf; 26 x 21 cm. Typescript letter signed in ink. (Box 1, Folder 32)
    Letter is addressed to "Eric," who is probably Eric Lister from the Portal Gallery. There are references to him being an acquaintance of Mr. Max (probably Max Wilk) and Mr. S.J.Perelman. Sam Smith is looking for Mr. Max's address so he can send him an invitation to his art show at the Camden Arts Centre in London NW3 6DG.
    Correspondence; Lister, Eric -- Correspondence; Portal Gallery (London, England); Smith, Sam, 1908- -- Correspondence
  - Unaddressed, unsigned letter, 1972 July 19; Smith, Sam, 1908-; 1 leaf; 26 x 21 cm. Typescript letter with ink additions. (Box 1, Folder 33)
    Typescript letter is not addressed or signed. There are ink additions of speech bubbles leading from the image of "The Founder" on the letterhead to the typescript.
  - Letter to Barbara Wilk, 1972 October 2; Smith, Sam, 1908-; 1 leaf; 26 x 21 cm. Typescript letter on pink paper with purple ink stamp of the sun, addressed and signed in ink. (Box 1, Folder 34)
    Sam Smith tells Barbara that he is working on two commissions and preparing for a lecture in Bournemouth to be called "Art and Laughter."
  - Letter to Barbara Wilk, 1973 August 21; Smith, Sam, 1908-; 1 leaf; 26 x 21 cm. Typescript letter on pink paper addressed and signed in ink. (Box 1, Folder 35)
    A personal letter discussing Barbara Wilk's poor health. Also discusses giving a lecture in Edinburgh and a film unit visiting his home to make a television piece of him at work.
  - Letter to Barbara Wilk, 1974 April 16; Smith, Sam, 1908-; 1 leaf; 26 x 21 cm. Typescript letter on pink paper addressed and signed in ink. Includes envelope with sun stamp in purple ink on verso. (Box 1, Folder 36)
    Discusses going to Toronto, Canada, for a "gigantic friendly international friendly arty conference," where there will also be an exhibition where some of his pieces will be displayed.
  - Letter to Max and Barbara Wilk, 1974 June; Smith, Sam, 1908-; 1 leaf; 20 x 16 cm. Manuscript letter in pen and black ink. Signed Samstone Y. Colander. Includes original envelope. (Box 1, Folder 37)
    Amusing letter possibly describing a visit to Africa.
    Correspondence; Wilk, Barbara -- Correspondence; Smith, Sam, 1908- -- Correspondence; Wilk, Max, 1920- -- Correspondence
  - Letter to Francie Wilk, 1974 July 18; Smith, Sam, 1908-; 1 leaf; 30 x 21 cm. Typescript letter on orange paper, addressed and signed in ink. (Box 1, Folder 38)
    Gives stories about horses, goats and Francie's parents.
    Correspondence; Begaye, Mary Frances -- Correspondence; Smith, Sam, 1908- -- Correspondence
  - Postcard to Max and Barbara Wilk, 1974 September 21; Smith, Sam, 1908-; 1 postcard; 15 x 11 cm. With a handwritten note in ink. (Box 1, Folder 39)
    Describes personal experiences in France.
    The postcard image depicts Les Eyzies-de-Tayac (Dordogne).
    Postcards; Wilk, Max, 1920- -- Correspondence; Wilk, Barbara -- Correspondence; Smith, Sam, 1908- -- Correspondence
  - Letter to Barbara Wilk, 1974 October 28; Smith, Sam, 1908-; 1 leaf; 26 x 21 cm. Typescript letter hand addressed and signed in ink. (Box 1, Folder 40)
    Discusses personal matters and makes mention of Eric, Lionel, and Frances.
  - Letter to Max and Barbara Wilk, 1975 November 29; Smith, Sam, 1908-; 1 leaf; 26 x 21 cm. Typescript letter on pink paper, addressed and signed in ink. Includes envelope with pen and ink on verso, "Isn't Loretta Young a beauty?" (Box 1, Folder 41)
    Discusses a book, but does not give the title. "The book is marvellous and it's quite extraordinary the way Max's presence can be felt on each page; quite unseen but there, lurking behind the Sheik of Araby and round the corner at the End of the Long Long Trail."
    Correspondence; Smith, Sam, 1908- -- Correspondence; Wilk, Max, 1920- -- Correspondence; Wilk, Barbara -- Correspondence
  - Letter to Max and Barbara Wilk, 1976 April 28; Smith, Sam, 1908-; 1 leaf; 26 x 21 cm. Typescript letter on pink paper, addresses and signed in orange ink. (Box 1, Folder 42)
    The letter makes reference to Max's book, but does not give the title. Sam also mentions a film unit being in his home to make a film for the Arts Council.
    Correspondence; Wilk, Max, 1920- -- Correspondence; Smith, Sam, 1908- -- Correspondence; Wilk, Barbara -- Correspondence
  - Letter to Max and Barbara Wilk, 1976 August 20; Smith, Sam, 1908-; 2 leaves Typescript letter addressed and signed in orange ink. Some extra illustration and corrections in black ink. Leaf one on pink paper, leaf 2 on white paper.; 26 x 21 cm. 2 leaves; 26 x 21 cm. Typescript letter addressed and signed in orange ink. Some extra illustration and corrections in black ink. First leaf on pink paper; leaf two on white paper. (Box 1, Folder 43)
    Discusses drought in south England, correspondence from Eric Lister, and needing to get started on another children's book.
    Correspondence; Smith, Sam, 1908- -- Correspondence; Lister, Eric -- Correspondence; Portal Gallery (London, England) -- Correspondence; Wilk, Barbara -- Correspondence; Wilk, Max, 1920- -- Correspondence
  - Letter to Max and Barbara Wilk, 1977 March 5; Smith, Sam, 1908-; 1 leaf; 26 x 21 cm. Typescript letter on pink paper. Addressed and signed in green ink. (Box 1, Folder 44)
    Describes Smith's affection for Lillian Gish and the preview of his film, Sam Smith, Genuine England made by the Arts Council.
    Correspondence; Arts Council of Great Britain -- Correspondence; Wilk, Max, 1920- -- Correspondence; Wilk, Barbara -- Correspondence; Smith, Sam, 1908- -- Correspondence
  - Letter to Max and Barbara Wilk, 1977 May 12; Smith, Sam, 1908-; 1 leaf; 26 x 21 cm. Typescript letter on pink paper, addressed and signed in green ink. (Box 1, Folder 45)
    Letter is mainly personal. Smith mentions that "Pres. Carter has won the hearts of the English." Smith also gives his well wishes to Frances.
    Correspondence; Smith, Sam, 1908- -- Correspondence; Wilk, Barbara -- Correspondence; Begaye, Mary Frances; Wilk, Max, 1920- -- Correspondence; Carter, Jimmy, 1924-
  - Letter to Max and Barbara Wilk, 1977 August; Smith, Sam, 1908-; 1 leaf, 2 pages; 26 x 21 cm. Typescript letter on pink paper, signed and addressed in orange ink. An extra note is added in black ink. (Box 1, Folder 46)
    The letter mentions a few different people, Frances, Kay Eddy (for whom he is working on some art pieces), Eric, and Lionel (for whom he is making an Adam and Eve set for their exhibition). In the extra note on the reverse, Sam mentions receiving a copy of the Arts Council film and that it had won an award in Australia.
    Correspondence; Lister, Eric; Wilk, Barbara -- Correspondence; Wilk, Max, 1920- -- Correspondence; Begaye, Mary Frances; Smith, Sam, 1908- -- Correspondence
  - Letter to Max and Barbara Wilk, 1978 January 1; Smith, Sam, 1908-; 1 leaf; 26 x 20 cm. Typescript letter on pink paper, addressed and signed in orange ink. Postscript written in black ink. (Box 1, Folder 47)
    Discusses welcoming the New Year, Smith's previous hospitalization, and house hunting.
  - Letter to Max Wilk, 1979 June 21; Smith, Sam, 1908-; 1 leaf; 26 x 21 cm. Typescript letter on pink paper, addressed and signed in black ink. (Box 1, Folder 48)
    Letter is personal, but mentions an upcoming show: "next October, when I am doing a show in a castle in Wales which has a leaning tower ..."
    Letterhead has a new mailing address: 21d Forde Park, Newton Abbot, Devon, England. Smith makes reference to furiously working after the year of moving house.
  - Letter to Max Wilk, 1979 October 29; Smith, Sam, 1908-; 1 leaf; 26 x 21 cm. Typescript letter on pink paper addressed and signed in red ink. (Box 1, Folder 49)
    Letter is personal in nature, but does mention finishing "a thing" for the Portal Gallery. There is also mention of "Ms Dawn Begaye" the Wilks' daughter Frances.
    Correspondence; Wilk, Max, 1920- -- Correspondence; Smith, Sam, 1908- -- Correspondence; Portal Gallery (London, England)
  - Letter to Barbara Wilk, before 1979; Smith, Sam, 1908-; 1 leaf; 30 x 21 cm. Typescript letter addressed and signed in green ink. Some corrections in ink. (Box 1, Folder 50)
    Letter discusses a trip to London once Sam receives word that the model for a "Beauty Queen" is complete and giving a lecture next January in London. He also mentions receiving a letter from a (Lady) Gloria Dale.
  - Letter to Max and Barbara Wilk, before 1979; Smith, Sam, 1908-; 1 leaf; 26 x 21 cm. Typescript letter addressed and signed in blue ink on Sam Smtih letterhead. (Box 1, Folder 51)
    Sam sends his regrets regarding a party and adds a postscript stating, "there is a lot developing on the Sam Smith pasture."
  - Letter to Max and Barbara Wilk, before 1979; Smith, Sam, 1908-; 1 leaf; 26 x 21 cm. Typescript letter on pink paper addressed and signed in ink. (Box 1, Folder 52)
    Sam tells Max and Barbara that his house is on the market and that he is moving to a town named Newton Abbot.
  - Letter to Max Wilk, 1980 September 22; Smith, Gladys [Jewett]; Smith, Sam, 1908-; 1 leaf, 2 pages; 26 x 21 cm. Manuscript letter on pink paper. (Box 1, Folder 53)
    Written by Gladys Smith on Sam Smith's behalf. Sam has had a stroke on August 1st and is in recovery. Gladys mentions that the Arts Council Exhibition of Sam Smith and H.C. Westermann will still go on from Dec. - Jan. at the Serpentine, London.
    Correspondence; Smith, Sam, 1908- -- Correspondence; Wilk, Max, 1920- -- Correspondence; Wilk, Barbara; Westermann, H. C. (Horace Clifford), 1922-1981; Arts Council of Great Britain; Serpentine Gallery; Begaye, Mary Frances
  - Letter to Max and Barbara Wilk, 1970s; Smith, Sam, 1908-; 1 leaf; 24 x 20 cm. Written in black ink, on Prince Rupert Hotel letterhead. (Box 1, Folder 54)
    Letter describes upcoming trip to North Wales and a later trip to Crete. Smith expresses his concern for knocking down Grand Central Station.
  - Card unaddressed, 1970s; Smith, Sam, 1908-; 1 card; 11 x 14 cm. Card with printed artwork on cover. Handwriten and signed in black ink. (Box 1, Folder 55)
    Smith mentions "Eric"--possibly Eric Lister--and a visit by two young Australians. Smith sends his New Year's wishes and an update about the conversion of his loft into a work space.
    New Year cards; Greeting cards; Smith, Sam, 1908- -- Correspondence
- Miscellaneous, Series VIII
  - Sam Smith: typescript (photocopy) of a speech, circa 1979-1980; Smith, Sam, 1908-; 5 leaves; 30 x 21 cm. (Box 1, Folder 56)
    This speech, produced for the Arts Council of Great Britain, was broadcast by the BBC (ca. 1979-1980).
    Typescripts; Arts Council of Great Britain; British Broadcasting Corporation
  - Shipping envelope to Barbara Wilk, 3 January 1973; Smith, Sam, 1908- (Box 1, Folder 57)
    Postage stamps; Envelopes (Stationery); Wilk, Barbara -- Archives; Smith, Sam, 1908- -- Archives
  - Woodblock printed wrapping paper, unknown; Smith, Sam, 1908-; 2 folded sheets; 41 x 23 cm. 2 off-white folded sheets of woodblock printed wrapping paper. (Box 4, Folder 12)
    Woodblock prints include "Sam Smith", a sail boat, a man shoeing a horse, an eagle, an upright piano, a bull, a crown, a horse-drawn carriage, etc. In red felt-tip pen one is marked No. 1 and No. 2. Invoice No. is highlighted in red. These must be examples of the papers in which Smith wrapped his commissions.
    wrapping paper; Wood engravings; Smith, Sam, 1908- -- Archives